Finding Aid for the The Andrew Nelson Lytle Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Series VIII. Family Papers
  - Insurance (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Life and burial (Robert L. Lytle), 1913-1936 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Legal (1 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Land records, 1890-1947 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Legal (2 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Wills and estate papers, 1852-1913 and undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Legal (3 of 3) (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Legal paper fragments, 1879-1934 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Fragments (1 of 2) (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Funeral of Joseph Hewlett Nelson, 1906 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Invitation to Art Reception, Soule College, 1893 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Playbill for Antigone (Pamela Lytle), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Fragments (2 of 2) (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Funeral of Joseph Hewlett Nelson, 1906 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Invitation to Art Reception, Soule College, 1893 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Playbill for Antigone (Pamela Lytle), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Series IX. Writings By Others
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Ade, Bill (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - “The Ring,” 9 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - B., E. [Barker, Edna Langdon?] (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Two untitled holograph poems marked “E.B., July 1934.” (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Cheney, Brainard (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - “I Choose To Die,” pages [i-iii], 1-83, bound typed manuscript signed by “Lon” (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Cheney. (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Cheney, Brainard (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - 1 typed page (292) from an unidentified work, probably by Cheney, with Lytle’s holograph comments on the reverse. (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Clark, S.T. (“Bill”) (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - “Democracy,” 1 page holograph manuscript, 1926 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - “I would know, o death, just where we met...,” 1 page typed manuscript, 1927 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - “The Poem,” 1 page holograph manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Davidson, Donald (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - “Assembly At Murfreesboro,” 2 page typed manuscript (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - “Fire On Belmont Street,” 2 page typed manuscript (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - “Twilight On Union Street,” 1 page typed manuscript (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - De Bellis, Jack (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - “A Name For Evil by Andrew Nelson Lytle,” pages [i], 1-18 typed manuscript, done for an English class in literary criticism at UCLA, 1958 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Dickey, James (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - “The Confrontation of the Hero,” pages 1-3, typed manuscript dated April, 1945 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - “Father and Sons,” pages 1-3, typed manuscript, was attached to a Dickey letter dated, November 3, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - “The Sprinter’s Mother,” pages 1-2, typed manuscript, was attached to a Dickey letter dated, November 14, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Dickinson, Carolyn (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - “Twig Masted,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Finlay, John (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - “A Voyage,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Flachmann, Michael Charles (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - “As I Like Begging,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - “I Walked With Kings,” 1 page typed manuscript (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - “The Night of Clowns,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - “The Truce,” 1 page typed manuscript (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - “Two Poems,” 1 page typed manuscript (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Foata, Anne (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - “La Lecon des Tenebres: The Edenic quest and its Christian solution in Andrew Lytle’s The Velvet Horn,” photocopy of article which appeared in Southern Literary Journal 16 (Fall, 1983): 71-95, signed by Foata. (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Gerber, Merrill Joan (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - “Miss Mosh,” pages [i], [1]-19, typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Gordon, Caroline (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Publicity blurb about Andrew Lytle, pages [1]-4, written for At The Moon’s Inn, [1941]. (See Box 11, Folder 32 for the final version) (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Hetrick, Larence (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - “Dream of Childhood,” 2 pages typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Johnson, Stanley (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - “Ships,” published as a Christmas card, sent to the Lytles as a Christmas card, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Koch, Claude (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - “Interview with Andrew Lytle,” pages 1-6 typed manuscript with holograph corrections. (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Lucas, Mark (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - “Chapter VIII, In The Inner Chamber: The Velvet Horn,” 27 pages typed manuscript with holograph comments. Published in The Southern Vision of Andrew Lytle, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - McDowell, Edward A. (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - “The high cost of living...,” 1 page typed manuscript, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - McNabb, Edward T., Jr. (Box 15, Folder 30)
    - “Landsend,” 1 page typed manuscript, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - Middleton, David (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - “The Patriarch,” 5 page typed manuscript, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - “The Shepherd,” 1 page typed manuscript, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 31)
    - “Thomas Tallis to William Byrd,” two photocopied pages from the Sewanee Review, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Milton, George Fort (Box 15, Folder 32)
    - Review of Bedford Forrest and His Critter Company, pages 1-5 typed manuscript, with holograph corrections, 1931 (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - Mullins, Helene (Box 15, Folder 33)
    - “The Suicide,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - Oras, Ants (Box 15, Folder 34)
    - 1 page typed manuscript poems signed by Oras, but possibly by his students:, Alver, Betti: “Ecstasy,” “The Iron Heaven,” “Is Life a Cage for Ever?” “Links,” “The Lovely Sister,” “Quasi una fabula,” “Snow in May,” “The Titans,” “Vision.” Suits, Gustav: “Abelard and Heloise.” Talvik, Heiti: “Chorus of Slaves,” “Evening Song,” “The Poet,” “Sunset.” (Box 15, Folder 34)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Owsley, Harriet (Box 15, Folder 35)
    - Untitled reminiscence of Andrew Lytle on his eightieth birthday, pages 1-5 typed manuscript, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 35)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - Pace, Rosalind (Box 15, Folder 36)
    - “The Word Made Flesh: A discussion of archetypal criticism and Andrew Lytle’s novel The Velvet Horn,” pages [i]-[iii], [1]-73, abstract 1-4 typed manuscript. Brown University, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 36)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - Quinn, Sydney Roberta (Box 15, Folder 37)
    - “Discertation on an Image,” pages [1]-3, typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - Simpson, Lewis P. (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - “Andrew Lytle: Artist and Critic,” pages [1]-3, typed manuscript, read on the program of “Andrew Lytle: A Celebration,” Sewanee Inn, Sewanee, Tennessee, December 3, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 38)
    - “Forward,” [to Southerners and Europeans] pages 1-10 typed manuscript, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - Smith, Ron (Box 15, Folder 39)
    - “The Quoth,” 1 page typed manuscript, 1985. Parody of Allen Tate’s “The Oath.” (Box 15, Folder 39)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 40)
    - [Stevenson, Alec Brock] (Box 15, Folder 40)
    - Untitled 1 page typed manuscript poem, signed “abs.” (Box 15, Folder 40)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 41)
    - Sullivan, Walter (Box 15, Folder 41)
    - “Andrew Lytle: A Personal Remembrance,” pages [1]-13, typed manuscript, three sets. (Box 15, Folder 41)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 42)
    - Sullivan, Walter (Box 15, Folder 42)
    - Chapter “V,” pages 63-76, page proofs, later published in Allen Tate: A Personal Recollection, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 42)
  - Identified (1 of 2) (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - Tate, Allen (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “The Buried Lake,” pages [1]-6, typed manuscript “part VI of a poem of some length, now in progress,” [1952]. (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “False Nightmare,” pages [1]-2, typed manuscript, [1934] (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “Fathers of Exile: Imaginary Autobiographies of Obscure Americans,” pages [i-ii], [1]-5 (Forward), typed manuscript written at “Benfolly, Montgomery County, Tennessee, May 23, 1933.” (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “Her Posture,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “Jubilo,” 1 page typed manuscript (front and back). (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “The Meaning of Life,” 1 page typed manuscript. See Tate letter of, November 2, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “Message From Abroad, Paris, November 1929 (To Andrew Lytle),” pages [1]-3 typed manuscript, signed by Allen Tate. See Tate letter of, November 3, 1929 (Box 15, Folder 43)
    - “The Oath,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 43)
  - Identified (2 of 2) (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - Tate, Allen (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - “Picnic At Cassis,” 1 page typed manuscript. See Tate letter of, November 2, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - “The Secret of the Captain (The Night before the Re-union),” pages [1]-3, typed manuscript, liberally annotated by Donald Davidson. (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - “The Secret of the Captain (The Night before the Re-union),” pages [1]-3, typed manuscript. See Tate letter of, June 9, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - “To The Lacedemonians...,” [1]-3 typed manuscript. See Tate letter of, June 17, 1932 (Box 15, Folder 44)
    - “To The Lacedemonians...,” [1]-3 typed manuscript with brief holograph note by Tate. (Box 15, Folder 44)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 45)
    - Tillinghast, Richard (Box 15, Folder 45)
    - “For A Teacher’s Wife, Dying of Cancer,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 15, Folder 45)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 46)
    - Wade, John Donald (Box 15, Folder 46)
    - “Andrew Lytle,” 1 page typed manuscript about Lytle. (Box 15, Folder 46)
  - Identified (Box 15, Folder 47)
    - Wade, Leila A. (Box 15, Folder 47)
    - “Lazy By Divine Right,” pages [1]-36, [], 10-13, 20-41, typed manuscript of a play in which Lytle portrayed the character “Turk.” Appears to be Lytle’s acting script with his notes, [1927] (Box 15, Folder 47)
  - Identified (2 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Wade, Leila A. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - “Lazy By Divine Right” (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Identified (3 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Wade, Leila A. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - “Lazy By Divine Right” (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Identified (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Warren, Robert Penn (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - “Conquest,” 1 page typed manuscript. “R.P.W., Oxford, October 23, 1928.” (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - “Hawthorne, Anderson and Frost,” typed manuscript, first page only of a book review published in 1928 in New Republic. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - “Kentucky Mountain Farm, III. History among the Rocks,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - “Kentucky Mountain Farm, IV. The Owl,” 1 page typed manuscript. “R.P.W., Oxford, October 23, 1928.” (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - “Late Subterfuge,” 1 page holograph manuscript (front and back) – not in Warren’s hand (possibly Isabel Howell). (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - “A Toast to Andrew Lytle,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Identified (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Westman, H. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - “What Is Psychotherapy?,” pages [1]-9, typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Identified (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Wright, Whittier (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - “Liberal Technics,” pages [1]-8, typed manuscript. Published in Vanderbilt student publication, The Gadfly, in, 1947 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - “Time Alone,” 1 page typed manuscript, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified (1 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - “An Effect Produced By Reading Andrew Lytle’s Essay, The Hind Tit,” pages [1]-17, typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified (2 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - “The Portrait of a Lady by Henry James,” [1]-7, typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified (3 of 3) (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - “And though within it no birds sing...” 1 page holograph manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - “Jesus has a table spread...” 1 page holograph manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - “Midnight in the Afternoon,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - “Stag Tracks,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - “A Three Sided Figure,” 1 page typed manuscript. (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Series X. Envelopes
  - Envelopes (1 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Envelopes (2 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Envelopes (3 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Envelopes (4 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Envelopes (5 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Envelopes (6 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Envelopes (7 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Envelopes (8 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Envelopes (9 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Envelopes (10 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Envelopes (11 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Envelopes (13 of 12) (Box 16, Folder 20)
- Series II. Writings
  - Novels (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Long Night (published 1936). (1 of 10) Long galleys, pages 66-84, with editor’s notes and markings. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Novels (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Long Night. (2 of 10) Long galleys, pages 85-96, with editor’s notes and markings. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Novels (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Long Night. (3 of 10) Long galleys, pages 97-108 (101 incomplete), with editor’s notes and markings. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Novels (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Long Night. (4 of 10) Long galleys, pages 109-114 (109 incomplete), with editor’s notes and markings. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Novels (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - The Long Night. (5 of 10) Long galleys, unnumbered fragments of pages, with editor’s notes and markings. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series IX. Writings By Others
  - Identified (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Porter, Katherine Anne (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - “Old Mortality,” pages [1]-18, long galleys from the Southern Review, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)